<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon concerning zeal for religion consistent with moderation preached at Edenburgh on Sunday the 27th of April, 1690, before the Lord High Commissioner and the Estates of Parliament of Scotland / by Mr. George Meldrum ...</title>
            <author>Meldrum, George, 1635?-1709.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50559</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1637</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9041</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12994878</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12994878</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96392</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50559)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96392)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 391:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon concerning zeal for religion consistent with moderation preached at Edenburgh on Sunday the 27th of April, 1690, before the Lord High Commissioner and the Estates of Parliament of Scotland / by Mr. George Meldrum ...</title>
                  <author>Meldrum, George, 1635?-1709.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 14, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>For Richard Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Edenburgh and reprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement on p. [2] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms CXXXVII, 5-6 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96392:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON CONCERNING <hi>Zeal for Religion,</hi> Conſiſtent with Moderation.</p>
            <p>Preached at <hi>EDENB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH</hi> On Sunday the 27th of <hi>April,</hi> 1690.</p>
            <p>BEFORE The Lord High Commiſſioner, and the Eſtates of PARLIAMENT of <hi>SCOTLAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY Mr. <hi>GEORGE MELDR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M,</hi> A Presbyterian Miniſter, and till of late one of the Epiſcopal Clergy of that Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>Edenburgh:</hi> and Reprinted at <hi>London,</hi> for <hi>Richard Baldwin,</hi> near the <hi>Black Bull</hi> in the <hi>Old-Baily.</hi> 1690.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="note">
            <pb facs="tcp:96392:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96392:2"/>
            <head>Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>THE Reverend Author of the following Diſcourſe, is ſo well known in his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey for his Learning and Piety, that there needs no Character of mine to Recommend his Sermon. Only I think fit to acquaint the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Reader, that he was Miniſter at <hi>Aber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deen,</hi> under the Epiſcopal Clergy, till within theſe few years, and that he left that Party upon the account of ſome Scruples, wherewith he has ſufficiently acquainted the World upon ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Occaſions ſince.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:96392:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96392:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSALM 137, ver. 5, 6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>If I forget thee, O Jeruſalem, let my right hand forget her cunning.</p>
                  <p>If I do not remember thee, Let my tongue cleave to the roof of my mouth!</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>The words of the Text follows.</p>
            <q>If I prefer not Jeruſalem above my chief joy.</q>
            <p>THis Pſalm ſeems to have been penned by ſome of the Prieſts, or the Levitical Singers, in the time of the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, it being their Office to ſing Pſalms, and Songs of praiſe unto God with the voice, and to play on Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Muſick, to his praiſe, as ye will ſee it, 1 <hi>Cron.</hi> 25, and ſomething like this of Singing, and uſing of Harps you have here in the 2, and 3. <hi>verſes</hi> of this Pſalm.</p>
            <p>In the firſt ſix <hi>Verſes,</hi> you have an account, of the condition and ſtate, they, and the people of God were in, at this time, and how they were affected therewith; Where were they? in <hi>Babylon,</hi> and Captivity there: and as in the firſt <hi>verſe, Sitting by the rivers of Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea,</hi> where there were many, <hi>By the rivers of Babylon, there we ſat down;</hi> and how are they affected? why, <hi>they weeped</hi> and this grief was not ſo much, for their own privat particular diſtreſs, as on the account of the deſolation of the Church, and of the ruine of the State; It was, <hi>when they remembred Zion,</hi> in the firſt <hi>verſe,</hi> and <hi>remembered Jeruſalem</hi> in the 5, and 6 <hi>verſes.</hi> Yea, ſo much were they taken up with this, That when they that had carried them away captives, deſired them to ſing the ſongs which they uſed to ſing in their own Land, (whether in mockage, or out of curioſity,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:96392:4"/>I ſhall not debate) Yet thoſe perſons, could not admit a thought of joyful ſongs, in a time, when <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and <hi>Zion</hi> was in ſuch diſtreſs: They had ſuch an abhorrence, at any thing like mirth at ſuch a time, that they ingenuouſly, and with great ſeriouſneſs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, That ere they forget <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> with its diſtreſs, they would rather chuſe never to ſing with their Tongue, or play with their hand while they live, <hi>Let my tongue cleave to the roof of my mouth, and my right hand forget her cunning:</hi> Yea ſo much are they taken up with the welfare of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and <hi>Zion,</hi> if it did not fare well with <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> they valied no joy, they rather wiſh ſuch things to themſelves, ere they forget her, whoſe welfare they count a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove their chief joy; <hi>If I prefer not Jeruſalem above my chief joy.</hi> Theſe laſt words of <hi>verſe</hi> 6, which I have choſen, for the ground of my following Exhortation, they deſcribe to us, the diſpoſition and temper of a gracious heart, what is that? They prefer the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick good, the welfare of Church and State, above their own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, <hi>If I prefer not</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>above my chief joy,</hi> let me never have skill or ability to ſing or play any more.</p>
            <p>Theſe words will be plain, if I ſhew you what is meant by <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem;</hi> and what by preferring <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to our chief Joy. And how ſhall we better underſtand what is meaned by <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> than by a reflection on <hi>Pſalm</hi> 122. where there is a deſcription of this <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> there is the Houſe of the Lord, <hi>verſes</hi> 1, 9. The place whither the Tribes go up, to the Teſtimony of <hi>Iſrael, verſe</hi> 4. It is then the place of the Publick Worſhip. <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is alſo the place, <hi>where the Thrones of Judgment are ſet, even the Thrones of the Houſe of</hi> David, <hi>verſe</hi> 5. The Seat of publick Juſtice, Therefore, I may well conclude, that by <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is meant here, both Church and State; the Church of God where is his Worſhip, and State where Juſtice is adminiſtrat; this is it's meant here by <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> if I prefer not the welfare of <hi>Jeruſalem, i. e.</hi> of the Church and State, <hi>above my chief joy;</hi> in the Hebrew it is, <hi>the head of my joy,</hi> the higheſt and chiefeſt of my joy and comfort, of all my private concerns and comforts, if I prefer not the publick good of Church and State, to the chiefeſt of theſe, let me never have any comfortable day any more.</p>
            <p>From this we may learn and obſerve, That it is the duty of all, and will be the practice of every good man, to prefer the publick good and welfare of Church and State, to their own private Intereſt, even to the higheſt of their private Comforts. Behold the frame of the People of God in the Text, <hi>If I prefer not</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>above my chief
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:96392:4"/>joy, then let my right hand forget her cunning.</hi> Ere we do any thing that looks not like a preferring of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to all our own privat con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns and comforts, we rather wiſh we never have a joyful or mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day after, <hi>If we prefer not</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>above our chief joy,</hi> ſee this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned and practiſed. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 122. <hi>ver.</hi> 6, 7. <hi>Pray for the Peace of</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>let them proſper that love thee, for my brethrens ſake, I will now ſay, peace be within thee.</hi> Joel. 2.17. <hi>Let the Prieſts, the Lord's Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, weep betwixt the Porch and the Altar, and ſay, Spare thy People, and give not thy Heritage to a Reproach.</hi> And Jer. 51.50. <hi>Remember the Lord afar off, and let</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>come into your mind.</hi> O remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber its ſtate; we will find this temper, and diſpoſition of heart, has poſſeſt the Saints of God in all Ages; what an eminent height of it was in <hi>Moſes, Exod.</hi> 32.11, 12, 31, 32. after the ſin of the golden Calf, when the Lord threatens to deſtroy the People, on that account, how pleads he? <hi>Lord, remember</hi> Abraham, Iſaac <hi>and</hi> Jacob, <hi>the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians will ſay, thou haſt brought them out for a miſchief, pardon this people, if not, blot me, I pray thee, out of the Book which thou haſt writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten.</hi> What a height of a publick ſpirit was this? and <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> though he had all the Honour and Comforts the Court could afford, <hi>Neh. chap.</hi> 1. Yet he faſted and weeped, and took no comfort, ſo long as <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> walls lay in rubbiſh, ſo much did this affect his heart, that the King could not but diſcern it in his Countenance; why art thou ſad, ſaid he? And here is the cauſe, (ſays he) <hi>The place of my Father's Sepulchre, and the City of</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>lies on heaps;</hi> See it alſo in <hi>Jer. chap</hi> 9. at the beginning, <hi>O that my head were waters, and my eyes a fountain of tears, that I might weep day and night for the ſlain of the daughter of my people.</hi> And what a height of this frame was in the holy Apoſtle <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 9.1. <hi>I could even be content to be accurſed from Chriſt for my kinſmen according to the fleſh.</hi> Time would fail me, to tell you of <hi>Joſhua, Uriah</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> and of <hi>Daniel,</hi> of <hi>Mordecai,</hi> and <hi>Eſther,</hi> and others of the Saints in former times; but if we would ſearch the Scriptures, every-where we will find that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of Religion, of the Church of God and their Country, lay nearer the Saints hearts, than their own particular. Their hearts trembled when it was in danger; when it is reproached it is a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to them. If it be in diſtreſs, they mourn; they mourn for <hi>Zion</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> Iſai. 66.10. <hi>Rejoyce for</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>all ye that mourn for her.</hi> 1 Sam. 4.13. Eli's <hi>heart trembled for the Ark of God. Zephan.</hi> 3.18. <hi>The reproach of her was a burden.</hi> And when in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, how fervent in Prayer are they? <hi>Pſalm</hi> 14.7. <hi>O that the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:96392:5"/>ſalvation of God were come out of</hi> Zion, <hi>when the Lord bringeth back the Captivity of his People,</hi> Jacob <hi>ſhall rejoyce, and</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſhall be glad.</hi> And <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. <hi>ver.</hi> 18. <hi>Do good in thy good pleaſure to</hi> Zion, <hi>and build up the walls of</hi> Jeruſalem. Pſal. 25.22. <hi>Redeem</hi> Iſrael, <hi>O God, out of all his troubles.</hi> And how reſtleſs are they in this? <hi>Iſai.</hi> 62.1, 6, 7. They will <hi>give him no reſt till he eſtabliſh</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>and make it a praiſe in the Earth.</hi> So you ſee the truth of the Doctrine, and there is good reaſon for it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Honour of God is concerned in it, more than any particular, and this is the great thing lyes near every good man's heart, God's honour. What wilt thou do to thy great Name? How are they troubled in their hearts when the Name of God is reproached?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Every particular perſon, is but a Member of the Society of Church and State, and the part is for the whole, and what is for the good of the Society, their good is wrapt up in it; they ſhould mind the good of the whole, more than their own private concern; hence the Spirit reſembles the Church to a Body, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. and 1 <hi>Cor. ch.</hi> 12. <hi>Eph</hi> 4. ſhewing, <hi>If one Member ſuffer, all the reſt ſuffer with it;</hi> ſo that all is for the Bodies good, and all Gifts are given for the advancing and edifying of the Body, we live not to our ſelves, neither dye we to our ſelves, but for God, and ſerving him in the publick Good; this much for the proof of the <hi>Doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For <hi>Application,</hi> I might, firſt, Take occaſion to lament how lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of this publick Spirit is to be ſeen among us? Ah! ah! there is matter to renew that old Complaint, <hi>All ſeek their own things, but few the things of Chriſt,</hi> Phil. 2.21. Which is contrair to that Precept, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.14. <hi>Seek not every one their own things, but every one the things of another.</hi> Alas! too many like that old fat Monk, of whom it is ſtoried, that ſtroaking down his Breaſt and his Belly, ſaid, <hi>Modo hic ſit bene,</hi> providing it be well with himſelf, cared little how the World went about him; ſo many care little how it go with Church or State, if it go well with their own particular: O! but this argues a ſordid frame of heart, that if it go well with themſelves, and they proſper, they care little how it goes with others about them. Alas! what a ſhameful ſin is this, and a cauſe of much ſin and wo, and a ſin that ſeminally and caſually contains moſt of other ſins; let us be humbled for it, and afterward beware of this, and that ſhall be the</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:96392:5"/>
2. <hi>Uſe</hi> of Exhortation, and here I would with all poſſible ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs commend two things to you. 1. Beware of a narrow ſelfiſh Diſpoſition. 2. I commend unto you, to labour for a Publick frame of Spirit, that like theſe in the Text, ye may prefer <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> above your chief Joy. 1. Then beware of a ſelfiſh Diſpoſition, that Self be neither your Principle nor End, I the rather urge this with Earneſtneſs, becauſe, firſt, I ſee this a very common Sin, and yet a Sin we are hardly convinced of. <hi>First,</hi> Selfiſhneſs is the moſt common ſin in the World, look either to Church or State, to Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrats or Miniſters, to High or to Low, ye may diſcover much of the prevalent influence of Selfiſhneſs. This is matter of Lamentation, yea, I think it is a ſad truth, that every Man and Woman among us, now ſince the Fall, is born with a ſelfiſh inclination, and are not eaſily convinced of the ſinfulneſs of it. Becauſe God hath made Man with a natural love to ſelf, and made it as a fundamental Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple and Law of Nature; therefore it is hard to make us ſenſible; when this Love gets out of due ſubordination to the Love of God, and out of that due correlation, to that Love we ought to have to our Neighbour as ourſelves. This makes us we are not eaſily convinced of it, and ſo hardly recovered from it. Some are ſo intent on Gain and enlarging their Eſtates, without regard to Juſtice or Charity, as if their deſire were, that they may place themſelves alone on the Earth, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.8. Others ſo intent on their Honour, and Riſing in the World, that they care not though they riſe by the Blood and Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of them that ſtand in their way; yea, ſuch is the Deceit of mens hearts in this matter, men may pretend the publick Good, when Self is at the bottom of all. Some will pretend they are for Peace, Order, and Publick Good, when it is that they and theirs may poſſeſs the fat Benefices of the Church or State. Sometimes Men may pretend to the Reforming of Abuſes, rectifying or preventing Diſorders, when Envy and Diſcontent, the caſting down others, and raiſing up themſelves acteth them, yea, the Honour of God may be pretended, when the exalting ourſelves and our own Party is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned: Yea, Miniſters, if they watch not, may be led to pray for ſelf, and preach for ſelf. This then being ſo common a ſin, how much need is there, to ſtir up all of you, to watch againſt a ſelfiſh diſpoſition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I would the rather call to this, becauſe, as it is a common, ſo it is a great and grievous ſin, a Mother ſin; I may ſay a ſelfiſh Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſition is much of the cauſe of all the ſin in the world, it is directly
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:96392:6"/>oppoſite to the love of God above all, and to the love of our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour as our ſelves, which is the ſum of the Law. A man that is ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſh, can with no ſincerity pray, <hi>Thy Will be done, thy Kingdom come,</hi> for he exalts his own Intereſt more than Gods, and his own Will above and againſt Gods: And this is the cauſe of much iniquity in the world, and this being ſo great a ſin, and a Mother-ſin, O hate it, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of it!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> This ſurely is a hurtful evil, hurtful to others, and hurtful to our ſelves, it is an Enemy to all Societies being contrair to the end of Society, to wit, the common Good, for it ſeeks mens private good above the common Good. And as it divides Intereſts, ſo it divides Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and makes Diviſions in the Church and State; this is contrair to the diſpoſition and temper that ſhould be in the Members of a Society, who ſhould be all animat by a common Spirit. There can be no promoting of publick Ends by a privat ſelfiſh Spirit. We cannot promot the publick Good without a publick Spirit. This is it which divideth all Societies; this occaſions all Jealouſies between King and People, all Emulation between Neighbour and Neighbour; this occcaſions diviſion in the State, and Schiſm in the Church, this is a great cauſe of War and Confuſion, Fraud and Oppreſſion, and what a world of miſchief would ſelfiſhneſs do, if Grace and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Providence did not put a ſtop to it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> It is hurtful to our ſelves, men loſe themſelves, by ſeeking themſelves, with the neglect of the common good. Men by their ſelfiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, they certainly loſe not only the peace of their own mind, which they might have by doing good, and aiming at the publick good, but ſet all others againſt them; and when they divide Intereſts from all men, all men divide Intereſts from them, for this is their Principle, that neglect of the Publick, is the way to be beſt preſerved, and the great ſafety of their own particular. This is the ſure way fooliſhly to ruine all; as if when a Houſe is in Fire, a Man ſhould think it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough it has not ſeized yet on my Chamber; or when a Ship is ſink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to look only to our own Cabin and Goods, without care to ſtop the common Leak: O let me beſeech you to beware of this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Let me beſeech you (dearly Beloved) labour for a Publick frame of Spirit, O imitat theſe Worthies in the Text, prefer <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to your chief Joy, in your eſteem, deſire, and endeavour, prefer the publick good of Church and State, above all our privat Concerns, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all your perſonal and privat Comforts. Is not this a more excellent end, than ſelfiſh Intereſt, even the pleaſing and glorifying of God
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:96392:6"/>in the promoting the publick Good? O that I could prevail with you in this, it would ſurely be your great Advantage, and ſure if ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ye regard the Honour of God, or your own true Intereſt, you cannot ſay me nay; Let me plead with you from theſe Reaſons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Honour of God is concerned in it. It's more concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the publick Good of Church and State, than in your own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Concern. And O! but the Honour of God lyes nigh to the heart of every one that loveth God; This is the end for which we were made.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Mind the publick Good more than your privat Intereſt, for this makes you like God and your Saviour Jeſus Chriſt. God is always doing Good to the Evil and Unthankful. Chriſt Jeſus from the Womb, to the Grave, by his Dying and Suffering, teaches us this Leſſon, even to mind others, and the Publick Good, <hi>He pleaſed not himſelf,</hi> Rom. 15.3. <hi>Let the ſame Mind be therefore in you, which was in Chriſt Jeſus, who made himſelf of no Reputation,</hi> Phil. 2.5, 7. Who gave himſelf for the good of others, <hi>and humbled himſelf unto Death, even the Death of the Croſs,</hi> v. 8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> O! but the Advantage of this would be unſpeakable, if all of us were brought to this Temper, to mind the publick Good more than our own. O how amiable a Creature would man be! and what a bleſſed Condition would the World be in! and all Societies, Kingdoms, Cities, and Churches be in, if Self were denyed, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one minded the common and publick God, above their own pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vat and perſonal Intereſt! This would prevent neglect of Duties, and doing of hurt to others, there would not be ſuch a thing as In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice, and uncharitableneſs among men, Emulation, Strife and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy; no divided Intereſt, and ſo no divided Affection, no diviſion in the State: No Jealouſie between the Ruler and Ruled, if this were. If there were complication of Intereſts, there would be an Union of Affections: As we ſee in Husband and Wife, in Parents and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. This were a good Policy in States men, and next to Piety towards God, which leadeth to the uniting People to God, and to favour with him, wherein all our Happineſs ſtands; and indeed what ever the World think of it, it is the greateſt Wiſdom and Policy. Next I ſay to this, the greateſt point of humane Policy for preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Commonwealths and Societies were, that the Governour and Governed have no divided Intereſt, ſo that the good or hurt of the one, is the good or hurt of the other, and there is no manner of hope
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:96392:7"/>that the one of them ſhall thrive by the ruine of the other. Then they would willingly take one another for better and for worſe, to ſtand and fall together. If the Politicians had the Skill and Will, to make ſuch a complication of Intereſts, betwixt Soveraign and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Ruler and Ruled, as the Wellfare and hurt of the one might depend on the Wellfare and hurt of the other, and make it viſible that all might underſtand it; Certainly Kingdoms and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths, might be Immortal, till either the wrath of an offended God, or the power of a Forraign Enemy ſhould diſſolve them, for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing within would do it, if Self did it not; and Self will not do it where there is ſuch Complication of Intereſts. O then ſtudy to be denied to Self, and to be of a publick frame of Spirit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Conſider this would be each one of our particular Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, the good of your Families and Poſterity depends on the good of the Publick, your own Honour is concerned in this. Will you tell me, which of theſe two were a more deſirable Inſcription on a Man's Tomb? <hi>Here lyes a man that for his Selfiſh ends, did his outmoſt to ruine both Church and State.</hi> Or, <hi>Here lies a Man that in all his Conſultations aimed at the Publick Good:</hi> And beſide the Peace, it would miniſter to mens Conſciences in Life and Death, our own temporal Peace and Welfare is wrapped up in the Publick Good. O! be like <hi>Mordecai. Eſth.</hi> 10.3. <hi>ſeeking always the wealth of his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> And beware as <hi>Baruch.</hi> Jer. 45.5. <hi>To ſeek great things for thy ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> If we neglect the Publick Good for our own particular Concerns, Heathens will riſe up in Judgement againſt us and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn us. O what a love to their Country did they ſhew! I ſhall but give you two Inſtances out of <hi>Plutarch,</hi> (ſee <hi>Plutarch</hi>'s <hi>Politicks,</hi> page 39, 40. in <hi>Octavo,</hi>) the one is of <hi>Cretinas</hi> the <hi>Magneſian</hi> and <hi>Hermias,</hi> betwixt whom there was great Animoſity, but in the time of the <hi>Mithridatick</hi> War, <hi>Cretinas</hi> ſaies, let <hi>Hermias</hi> have the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and I ſhall remove from the City, for I am afraid that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention deſtroy the Common-wealth; but if he will not, let him leave the Country and Government; and <hi>Hermias</hi> accepts the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and acknowledgeth that <hi>Certinas</hi> was the more Warlike, and ſit for the Government, and ſo removed himſelf and his Family. The other inſtance is of <hi>Timeſias Clazomenius,</hi> an excellent man, yet becauſe he did inhance all the Government, he contracted the Envy and Hatred of the People, of which he was ignorant till one day, as he paſſed by ſome Children, who had catched a Bird in a Gin,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:96392:7"/>and one of them bruiſing the Birds Head, cruſhed its Brains, the reſt ſaid to him, we wiſh thou had ſo bruiſed the Head of <hi>Timeſias:</hi> the Children not knowing that <hi>Timeſias</hi> was hearing them; but he hearing them, began to conſider in himſelf whence the hatred of the People had ariſen, which was now in the mouths of Children, and finding that his Government was unpleaſing to them, immediatly he packs up all and reſolves to leave the City and Country. This ſaies <hi>Plutarch</hi> is a ſaying worthy of a noble Mind, <hi>Amo liberos, ſed Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am magis amo.</hi> I ſay, if we mind not Publick Good, Heathens will riſe up againſt us, and Condemn us. Ye may now ask, How ſhall we attain to this frame of Spirit? And ſecondly, What ſhall we do for the Publick Good? <hi>1ſt.</hi> What ſhall I do to attain this publick frame of Spirit, that I may be of a temper, to prefer <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to my chief joy?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> I beſeech you, Sirs, meditate ſeriouſly on the Motives, I layed before you, at this time, until you get ſuitable Affections and Reſolutions raiſed in your Hearts, Conſideration is a chief Mean to this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Pray much to God for this Frame, he is the Giver of all good Gifts, he giveth liberally and upbraideth not, <hi>Ja.</hi> 1. v. 5, 17.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Labour for more love to God, and love to your Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours; if there were more Catholick Charity, more ſincere Love to God above all, and more Charity to our Neighbours, it would make us to ſeek more the Publick Good than our own.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Eye the Example of the Lord Jeſus, and his Saints and Servants, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.1, 2. Mind theſe things ſeriouſly, and ſeek of God that he would work them in you.</p>
            <p>Next you may ask, What ſhall we do for the Publick Good? there are ſome things, that even the meaneſt, in their moſt private Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city may do for the Publick Good; other things more incumbent to the Honourable Members of the High Court of Parliament, that they may do for the publick Good.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Some things the meaneſt in their moſt private Capacity may do for the publick Good. The meaneſt of all may, 1. Pray for the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, this is our Duty, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 122.6. <hi>Pray for the peace of Jeruſalem, peace be within thy walls, and proſperity within thy palaces,</hi> pray for this; this is it that all may do, and all ought to do, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62.6, 7. <hi>Ye that make mention of the Lord, and are the Lord's remembrancers give him no reſt, keep no ſilence, till be make Jeruſalem a praiſe on the earth.</hi> Its God only that ſhakes Kingdoms and Churches, and God only can e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh Kingdoms and Churches, and he cannot only Stabliſh but
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:96392:8"/>make them a Praiſe again upon the Earth. O ſeek him that he would ſettle Church and State again, and ſeek it importunately, the thing is weighty, and the time dangerous, and give him no reſt; he loves a holy Impudence and Importunity in this, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.8.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I recommend to you, Labour to be at Peace with God, or elſe your Prayers will come no ſpeed, <hi>Job<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 22.21. Acquaint thy ſelf with God, and be at Peace, and ſo ſhall good come unto thee: O! Peace with God quiets all; <hi>Tranquillus Dei tranquillat omnia.</hi> Job. 34.29. <hi>If he give quietneſs, who then can make trouble?</hi> O<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> therefore make Peace with God! This all of us ſhould endeavour after.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I recommend to you for the publick Good, Turn away every one of you from that which may obſtruct the publick Good, every one of you adds Fuel to the Fire, to the common Fire. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to turn from your Provocations; <hi>Your Iniquities ſeparate between you and your God, your ſins hides his face from you,</hi> Iſai. 59.2. <hi>Your Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities turns away good things from you,</hi> Jer. 5.25. Therefore turn every one of you from the evil of your way; away with Pride and Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, away with Unrighteouſneſs and Ungodlineſs; away with Fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs and Drunkenneſs, with Injuſtice and Oppreſſion, and ſo Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity ſhall not be your ruine.</p>
            <p n="4">4. I beſeech theſe in the moſt private Capacity, Labour what ye can to get theſe things that contribute for the Eſtabliſhing and Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement of Church and State; And what is that? even Righteouſneſs and Holineſs: Prov. 14.34. <hi>Righteouſneſs exalteth a Nation, but Sin is a reproach to any people.</hi> Holineſs, Mercy and Truth, Righteouſneſs and Meekneſs, Love, Charity and Juſtice. Iſai. 33.6. <hi>Wiſdom and ſtrength is the ſtability of thy times;</hi> and theſe are the things that tends to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Good, and therefore ſeek after them; and <hi>above all theſe things, put on Charity which is the Bond of Perfectneſs,</hi> Col. 3.14. Follow Peace, and love all men, eſpecially theſe of the Houſhold of Faith.</p>
            <p>Now theſe things, Perſons in the meaneſt Capacity may do. And I would humbly offer in the next place, ſome Things to the Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Members of the High Court of Parliament, as more eſpecially incumbent to them, in ſuch a Caſe as this. And if any ſhould ask, Who are you that ſhould give Advice to ſo high and honourable a Court? I humbly acknowledge my own meanneſs and unfitneſs for this Work, and would gladly have declined it if I could, but what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever my meanneſs be, I am a Servant of a great Maſter, before whom the greateſt on Earth are but as Graſhoppers; and if I have
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:96392:8"/>Warrand from him to ſpeak, I muſt not forbear, for fear of you leaſt he confound me before you, but I hope, I ſhall deliver nothing, but what is agreeable to his Word, and with all due Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility.</p>
            <p>And firſt, I recommend to you to be at Peace among your ſelves, and ſtudy to unite in ſincere Aims and Endeavours, for the publick Good of Church and State. This is the great thing needful in this matter. It is ſtoried of <hi>Themistocles</hi> and <hi>Aristides</hi> the <hi>Athenians,</hi> when ſent upon a publick Work, they agreed well, notwithſtanding of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny private Animoſity that was betwixt them. <hi>Come,</hi> ſays <hi>Ariſtides, let us lay aſide our Differences, and leave them upon the Borders of the</hi> Athenians, <hi>tho' we ſhould be neceſſitat to take them up again when the Work is done.</hi> O lay aſide Diſſerences, and remember our Saviour's word, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.25. <hi>Every Kingdom divided againſt it ſelf, ſhall be brought to Deſolation;</hi> this is your Adverſaries great Strength, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore take heed of this; I think <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> when Difference grows, ſhould be jealous, leaſt the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> have a Hand in this Matter, for <hi>Divide &amp; Impera,</hi> is her Maxime. But ſurely to unite in Common Good, is the great Duty of all.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing I recommend to you. O ſtudy by your Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample and Authority, to Diſgrace and Suppreſs all Debauchery and Impiety in the Country and Armies, remember that Word, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.30. <hi>Him that honoureth me I will honour, and he that deſpiſeth me ſhall be lightly eſteemed.</hi> Remember it, it's not enough to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs a Zeal againſt Arbitrarineſs in the State, or Popery in the Church, if we continue by Debauchery and Impiety to prophane our Holy Religion; this is no leſs offenſive to God than Popery; God expects from us Reformation of our Hearts and Lives, that as we profeſs a more Holy Religion than others, ſo we may lead more holy Lives, elſe we cannot expect God will be with us; but our Sins will provoke God to repent of the Good he thought to have to done, and to return to do us evil after he has done us good, <hi>Jer.</hi> 18.10. and <hi>Joſh.</hi> 23.15. our Sin will be the greater, and the Judgment the more heavy, that it is after ſo wonderful a Revelation: And no Wiſdom or Strength will keep off Wrath, if we go on in Sin; <hi>Ezra</hi> 9.14. And there is nothing feareth me more than that. Alas, we are not reformed and become better, by all that God hath done, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 9.13, 14. Beſtir your ſelves, noble Patriots; O ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy by your own Example to diſgrace the hateful Sins of Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and Swearing, of Filthineſs and Drunkenneſs, of Pride and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:96392:9"/>of Oppreſſion, and all Injuſtice, and endeavour to ſuppreſs theſe and ſuch like Sins, as by a due Execution of Laws made, ſo by a ſupply where there is any defect of ſuch wholſome Laws. And I wiſh a due care may be taken to ſuppreſs Debauchery in the Army. It is a common regrate that too many in it, I ſpeak not of all, I know the contrary of ſome, but too many neither fear God nor regard Man. There is indeed to look to it, that they be Men of Skill and Fidelity, and not Impious, for how can they be true to Man, who have no fear of God, the Debaucheries of ſome, and the Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularities of others, doth much prejudice to the common Cauſe, and both ought to be reſtrained. Certainly it is a ſhame for thoſe, who ſtand up for a holy Religion, to be leading filthy lives, Curſing and Damming on the Streets, Drinking and Debauching, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you reſtrain theſe. Surely at ſuch a time, there is need both People and Souldiers mind that word, <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.9, 14. <hi>When the hoſt goeth forth againſt the enemy, then keep thee far from every wicked thing, for the Lord thy God is among you:</hi> and if he ſee any unclean thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, he will leave you to fall before your Enemies; this holy care were the way to Victory and Peace. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 81.13. <hi>O that my people had hearkened unto me, and Iſrael had walked in my ways. I ſhould have ſoon ſubdued their enemies, and turned my hand againſt their adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries. The haters of the Lord ſhould have ſubmitted themſelves to him, but for them they ſhould have remained for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> I would humbly offer this as my advice, go forward zealouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in ſetling the Government of the Church of Chriſt, according to his own appointment. This is a choice mean to promote Piety, and to ſuppreſs Sin. I recommend to you that word of <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> Ezra. 7.23. <hi>Whatſoever is commanded by the God of Heaven, let it be done di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently for the Houſe of the God of Heaven, for why ſhould wrath come from the God of Heaven upon the Realm of the King and his Sons.</hi> I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but commend you, and bleſs the Lord, that with ſo much Unity and Harmony you have gone ſome footſteps already, go on, and the Lord be with you, and let none give way to theſe prejudices, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſome endeavour to poſſeſs mens minds againſt Presbyterial Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, as an intollerable yoke and rigid, as ſome Pamphlets now paſſing would repreſent it; for if you give way to ſuch, ye may caſt at the Chriſtian Religion ere long, for it hath been evil ſpoken of by the Adverſaries; and tho there ought to be a due Zeal againſt Error and Vice, yet I am confident there ſhall be that due modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which the Goſpel preſcribes, uſed toward all that are Pious and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:96392:9"/>Orthodox, that ſhall be ſatisfying and pleading to every one that loveth truth and holineſs: Neither, I beſeech you, impute the irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Practices of ſome unto the Principles of the whole Party, for theſe things we do diſown. I am ſorry for the Sufferings of any, but if any had deſigned a repreſentation of their Suffering, I wiſh it had wanted that Gall and Venome againſt the Civil Government, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſome Pamphlets are filled, and that there had been more Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, Ingenuity, and Honeſty; uſed in relating matters of Fact, the want of which perhaps may occaſion ſuch a ſearch as may diſcover, that the Sufferings of ſome, has been rather the effect of their own ſcandalous ſins, than of others hands. And tho' I have a great Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to all that are pious and ſound in the Principal Doctrines of the Faith, tho' they differ in leſſer things; yet I muſt crave leave freely to profeſs, before this great Auditory, that ere I did intrude my ſelf, or conſent to be obtruded on an unwilling People (as it was in moſt places of the Weſt) I had rather beg my Fraught to have carried me over to <hi>America,</hi> to preach to a willing People: And it is an old Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non in the Church, <hi>Nemo invitus obtrudatur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. As I beſeech you to advance Holineſs toward God, ſo endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to promote Righteouſneſs toward Man, that in all Courts of Judicature, there may be ſuch Judges as are mentioned, <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.21. <hi>Men fearing God, loving truth, and hating covetouſneſs;</hi> and <hi>charge them,</hi> as <hi>Deut.</hi> 1.16, 17. <hi>That ſuch judge righteouſly between man and man, and have no reſpect of perſons in judgment, for they judge for the Lord.</hi> And provide, as much as in you lyeth, that there be no partiality, nor perverting, nor delay of Juſtice, but that Judgment may run down like a Stream, and Righteouſneſs like a mighty River.</p>
            <p n="5">5. I humbly beſeech you of that Honourable Court, conſider what you may do for the Peace and Safety of the Country; its Caſe may be better known to many of you, than to me; yet I muſt crave leave to repreſent unto you the Caſe, eſpecially of ſome Northern parts; ſome are ravaged and ſpoiled with ſome barbarous Highlanders, and others burdened with Free-quarter, for want of the pay of the Army, and the Cries of the Poor cry for your pity, and call for your ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy help. Ye that ſettled the Government, will ye not uphold it? and ſtudy the ſafety of the Country under it? If this Ruine fall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your hand, it may ruine Poſterity, ruine Religion, and prove a great grief of heart to you, that are wanting of doing your duty,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:96392:10"/>
               <hi>while it is in the power of your hand to do it,</hi> Eccl. 9.10. I preſume not to preſcribe Methods to you, but humbly plead the Cauſe of the Diſtreſt, and that ye would conſider the Danger we are in.</p>
            <p n="6">6. I recommend to you the Care of the Education of Youth, the Viſiting and Reforming of Schools and Colledges, and the Caſe of the Children of ſome Great Ones now abroad, at Popiſh Schools. It may be worth your Conſideration, what may be done, to recover and reduce them, and to prevent the like in time coming.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, Study to promote Peace in the Nation, of Unity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong your ſelves, and Charity among all: Mind theſe things ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly; and with theſe two Qualifications I leave them.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. What ye do in theſe things, do it ſincerely, from right Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, as ye would approve your ſelves to God; for tho' ye do good, if ye do it not in a right manner, you loſe your reward of him. <hi>Ez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi> 4.2. I read of ſome, when the People were going to build the Temple, ſaid, <hi>Come, let us build with you,</hi> and yet deſigned but to mar the work; God forbid that there be any ſuch among you.</item>
               <item>2. Time is precious, and what ye do, do diligently and without delay, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 9.10. <hi>Do it with all your might:</hi> Remember you muſt be Accountable ere long to God for every Opportunity put in your Hand. Not only will God reckon with you for the evil you do, but for the Good ye might have done, and did it not; And therefore as ye would not have grief in your Heart, for neglect of it, at Death and Judgment, improve Seaſons and Opportunities for doing good. I leave one Word with you, <hi>Eſth.</hi> 4.13, 14. It is <hi>Mordecai</hi>'s word to <hi>Eſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her, Mordecai</hi> commanded to anſwer <hi>Esther, Think not with thy ſelf, thou ſhalt eſcape in the King's Houſe, more than all the Jews; for if thou altogether hold thy Peace at this time, then ſhall their Enlargement and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance ariſe to the Jews from another place, but thou and thy fathers houſe ſhall be deſtroyed: and who knoweth, whether thou art come to the Kingdom for ſuch a time as this.</hi> God bleſs what hath been ſpoken, and to Him be Glory for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:96392:10"/>
            <head>Books Printed for <hi>Richard Baldwin.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Cabinet Open'd, or the Secret Hiſtory of Madam <hi>de Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non,</hi> with the <hi>French</hi> King. Tranſlated from the <hi>French</hi> Copy.</p>
            <p>The Memoirs of Monſieur <hi>Deageant:</hi> Containing the moſt ſecret Tranſactions and Aſſairs of <hi>France,</hi> from the Death of <hi>Henry</hi> IV. till the beginning of the Miniſtry of Cardinal <hi>de Richelieu.</hi> To which is added, a particular Relation of the Archbiſhop of <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brun</hi>'s Voyage into <hi>England,</hi> and of his Negotiation for the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Roman Catholick Religion here; together with the Duke of <hi>Buckingham</hi>'s Letters to the ſaid Arch-Biſhop about the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of that Affair: Which happen'd the laſt Years of K. <hi>James</hi> I, his Reign. Faithfully Tranſlated out of the <hi>French</hi> Original.</p>
            <p>The Hiſtory of the moſt illuſtrious <hi>William</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange:</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd from the firſt Founders of the Ancient Houſe of <hi>Naſſau:</hi> Together with the moſt conſiderable Actions of this preſent Prince. <hi>The Second Ed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Collection of Fourteen Papers, relating to the Affairs of Church and State, in the Reign of the late K. <hi>James.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Character of a Trimmer. His Opinion of I. The Laws and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. II. Proteſtant Religion. III. The Papiſts. IV. Foreign Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs. By the honourable Sir <hi>W Coventry.</hi> The Third Edition carefully Corrected, and cleared from the Errors of the Firſt Impreſſion.</p>
            <p>An Impartial Relation of the Illegal Proceedings againſt St. <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> Colledge in <hi>Oxon,</hi> in the Year of our Lord 1687. Contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing only Matters of Fact as they occurred. <hi>The Second Edition.</hi> To which is added the moſt remarkable paſſages, omitted in the former. Collected by a Fellow of the ſaid Colledge.</p>
            <p>The Abſolute Neceſſity of ſtanding vigorouſly by the preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment: Or, a View of what both Church men and Diſſenters muſt expect, if by their unhappy Diviſions, Popery and Tyranny ſhould return again.</p>
            <p>The Juſtice of the Parliament, in inflicting of Puniſhments ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent to Offences, vindicated; and the Lawfulneſs of the Preſent Government aſſerted.</p>
            <p>An Account of Mr. <hi>Parkinſon</hi>'s Expulſion from the Univerſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> in the late Times; in vindication of him from the falſe Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſions caſt upon him, in a late Pamphlet, entituled, <hi>The Hiſtory of Paſſive Obedience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The way to Peace among all Proteſtants; being a Letter of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation, ſent by Bp. <hi>Ridley</hi> to Bp. <hi>Hooper.</hi> By Mr. <hi>Sam. Johnſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Purgatory prov'd by Miracles: Collected out of <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> Authors. With ſome remarkable Hiſtories relating to <hi>Britiſh, Engliſh,</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> Saints. With a Preface concerning their Miracles. By Mr. <hi>Samuel Johnſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:96392:11"/>
A Seaſonable Diſcourſe, ſhewing the Unreaſonableneſs and Miſchiefs of Impoſitions in Matters of Religion: Recommended to ſerious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration. By Mr. <hi>Andrew Marvell,</hi> late Member of Parliament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Revolter.</hi> A Tragi-Comedy, acted between the Hind and Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and <hi>Religio Laici.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Collection of Poems, Satyrs, and Songs, againſt Popery and Tyranny. In Four Parts.</p>
            <p>An Anſwer to the Bp. of <hi>Rocheſter</hi>'s firſt and ſecond Letters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Intreigues of the <hi>French</hi> King at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> to imbroil Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom; diſcover'd in ſeveral Diſpatches paſt between him and the late Grand Seignior, Grand Vizier, and Count <hi>Teckley;</hi> all of them found among that Count's Papers. With ſome Reflections upon them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Plain Engliſh:</hi> In relation to the real and pretended Friends to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Monarchy. Humbly offered to the Conſideration of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and his Great Council, the Lords and Commons in Parliament Aſſembled. <hi>The Second Edition.</hi> With a ſhort Preface, and an Appen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dix, concerning the Coronation-Oath adminiſtred to K. <hi>James</hi> II.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The New Non conformiſt:</hi> Or, Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Caſe in Preaching after a Deprivation, incurr'd by the expreſs Words of a Statute: Fairly ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and examined. With ſhort Reflections upon Mr. <hi>Cook</hi>'s Sermon, <hi>Feb.</hi> 2. 1690, which was Licens'd by the Arch-Biſhops Chaplain.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Fate of France:</hi> A Diſcourſe wherein, after having Anſwered the groundleſs Exceptions that are made againſt the lawful conduct of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> in ſecuring themſelves from Popiſh Tyranny, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> it is ſhewed, That by the <hi>Happy Revolution</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> all the Deſigns of the <hi>French</hi> King for the <hi>Univerſal Monarchy,</hi> are diſappoined; and the rational grounds to believe his Downfal near. In Three Dialogues betwixt Father <hi>Petre,</hi> Father <hi>La Chaize,</hi> and <hi>two Proteſtant Gentlemen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Anatomy of a Jacobite-Tory:</hi> In a Dialogue between <hi>Whig</hi> and <hi>Tory,</hi> occaſioned by the Act for Recognizing K. <hi>William</hi> and Q. <hi>Mary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Great Baſtard Protector of the Little One.</hi> Done out of <hi>French.</hi> And for which the <hi>French</hi> King put forth a Proclamation, with a Reward of Five thouſand <hi>Louis d'Ors,</hi> to diſcover the Author.</p>
            <p>A true Narrative of the Murders, Cruelties, and Oppreſſions, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petrated on the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> by the late King <hi>James</hi>'s Agents, ſince his Arrival there. Publiſhed for the Information of the <hi>Jaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bites,</hi> that endeavour his Return again.</p>
            <p>Reflections upon a Form of Prayer, lately ſet forth for the <hi>Jacobites</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and of an <hi>Abhorrence</hi> tendred by the late King, to ſome of our <hi>Diſſenting Biſhops,</hi> upon his preſent Majeſty's Landing.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
